Guide to the Papers of Jacques Judah Lyons (1813-1877), undated, 1705-1885, 1908, 1911-1914, 1917-1919, 1933, 1950 *P-15
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, NY
- Series I: Manuscripts, undated, 1705, 1709-1880, 1933, 1950; 3.75 linear feet. Boxes 1-6A.
  - Newspaper clippings on various subjects, undated, 1860 (Box 6, Folder 336)
  - Newspaper clipping regarding presentation of flag by Mrs. Commodore Levy, circa 1862 (Box 6, Folder 337)
  - Lecture by J.J. Lyons on the history of the Jews, given before the Hebrew Religious and Literary Library Association, undated (Box 6, Folder 338)
  - Calendar of events taken from the Occident,Asmonean, and Stein's Chronological Handbuch, undated (Box 6, Folder 339)
  - Prayer on the death of Lincoln, April 19, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 340)
  - Sermon by J.J. Lyons on the death of Pres. William Henry Harrison, circa 1841 (Box 6, Folder 341)
  - Book of Selichot by J. J. Lyons written in Surinam (Hebrew), undated (Box 6)
  - Manual containing calendar and instructions for various occasions, undated (Box 6)
  - Letter to Lyons and notes on Hebrew grammar by Joshua Seixas, undated (Box 6)
  - Manuscript Items relating to the Civil War, including letters, 1861-1865 (Box 6)
  - Various letters to J.J. Lyons: 1839 from M. Lyons, 1865 from B'nai Jeshurun, NYC, 1848, 1860 from J.P. Levy, 1876 from E. Judah?, 1839, 1848, 1860, 1865, 1876 (Box 6)
  - Hebrew salutatory at a graduation by Miss Regina Noe (Hebrew), undated (Box 6)
  - Hebrew epitaph of Isaac Abraham Adolphus (d. 1774) copied by Lyons (Hebrew), undated (Box 6)
  - Various resolutions, notes, etc. regarding K.K.S.I., undated, 1839, 1859 (Box 6)
  - Notes on J.J. Lyons taken from the archives in Paramaribo, 1950 (Box 6)
  - Eulogy on the death of Naphtali Phillips, 1870 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clipping of speech of Lyons at end of Civil War, 1865 (Box 6)
  - Sermon for Thanksgiving Day after Civil War, October 1865 (Box 6)
  - Two prayers on the death of Abraham Lincoln, 1865 (Box 6)
  - Speech by Lyons urging support of U.S. Sanitary Commission, undated (Box 6)
  - Speech by Lyons at exercises at Polonies Talmud Torah, 1876 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous notes, etc., made by J.J. Lyons (Hebrew, Dutch), undated (Box 6A)
  - Fragment of sermon by Lyons (?), undated (Box 6A)
  - Sermon by Lyons given on the centennial of the USA, 1876 (Box 6A)
  - Sermon given in Surinam by J.J. Lyons (Dutch), 1835 (Box 6A)
  - Curriculum guide for Passover, undated (Box 6A)
  - Miscellaneous notes, etc. by Lyons (Hebrew, Portuguese), undated, 1855, 1871, 1883, 1933 (Box 6A)
  - Manuscript prayer for the dedication of a synagogue (Hebrew), undated (Box 6A)
  - Miscellaneous booklet of prayers, written during the Civil War (Hebrew and English translation), circa 1860s (Box 6A)
  - Fragments of the Daniel Gomez ledger books (oversized, see Box #14 (items 48a-48g)), undated, 1727, 1739-1753 (Box 6A)
  - Sketch by Naphtali Phillips (book), 1863 (Box 6A)
- Series II: Notebooks, undated, 1863, 1872; .5 linear feet. Box 7.
  This series is composed of four notebooks and contains an address by Charles P. Daly at the Hebrew Benevolent Society of New York entitled "The Settlement of the Jews in North America."
  - Book no. 1 as per catalogue, undated (Box 7)
  - (Book no. 2 is located in Box 5, Item #324)
  - Book no. 3 as per catalogue, undated (Box 7)
  - Book no. 4 as per catalogue, undated (Box 7)
  - Book no. 5 as per catalogue, undated (Box 7)
  - Sketch by Naphtali Phillips (book), 1863 (Box 7)
  - "The Settlement of the Jews in North America", by Charles P. Daly. Address at the 50thanniversary of the Hebrew Benevolent Society of New York (article pasted in book), April 11, 1872 (Box 7)
- Series III: Scrapbooks, 1760-1786, 1812-1885; 1.5 linear feet. Boxes 8-10.
  This series has scrapbooks with newspaper clippings and notices as well as a watercolor of the first Bnai Jeshrun and a watercolor of Grand Island.
  - Scrapbook I (5f) (Dutch, English, Hebrew)(oversized, see Box #14 (items 49a-50) and Cabinet 16), 1812-1859 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook I, [Copy of] (5f) (Box 9)
  - Scrapbook II, 1837-1885 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook III, 1816, 1822, 1824, 1830, 1833-1858 (Box 10)
- Series IV: Minute Book, undated, 1760-1786; .25 linear feet. Box 10A.
  This series contains a minute book with meeting minutes belonging to Congregation Shearith Israel and Lyons' notes.
  - Minute Book, Congregation Shearith Israel, 1760-1786 (Box 10A)
  - Cover to Minute Book, Congregation Shearith Israel, 1760-1786 (Box 10A)
  - Lyons: Notebook of Shearith Israel, undated (Box 10A)
- Series V: Correspondence, undated, 1908, 1911-1914, 1917-1919; .25 linear feet. Box 11.
  The series consists of letters to Julius J. Lyons, both business and about his father's memorial and the Lyons Collection.
  - Correspondence of Lyons Collection Committee (not microfilmed), 1908, 1912-1914, 1919 (Box 11)
  - Papers of Lyons Collection Committee (not microfilmed), undated, 1911, 1917-1919 (Box 11)
  - Papers etc. of Lyons Collection Committee (not microfilmed), undated, 1911 (Box 11)
- Series VI: Books, 1783-1804; 1.5 linear feet. Box 12 (OS3).
  This series contains one oversized box that consists of a synagogue subscription list and ship log.
  - Log book of the ship "Sansom", January 31, 1798 (Box 12(OS3))
  - Record of subscriptions to Shearith Israel, 1783-1804 (Box 12(OS3))
- Oversized Separated Material, 1730, 1738-1745, 1760, 1785, 1787, 1796-1797, 1803, 1817, 1819, 1826, 1829, 1839, 1843, 1846, 1871; 4.3 linear feet. Boxes 13 (OS6) and 14 (OS1).
  - Noah's Weekly Messenger (separated from Box 1, Item #2), July 23, 1843 (Box 13(OS6), Folder 1)
  - New York Enquirer, vol. 1, no. 3 (separated from Box 1, Item #3), July 3, 1826 (Box 13(OS6), Folder 2)
  - Pennsylvania Packet and Daily Advertiser. Containing anecdote regarding Oliver Cromwell and the Jew (separated from Box 1, Item #8), December 12, 1785 (Box 13(OS6), Folder 3)
  - Resolution of K.K.S.I. to Sir Moses Montefiore regarding his visit to Russia (separated from Box 1, Item #59), September 17, 1846 (Box 13(OS6), Folder 4)
  - Copy of offerings rendered for the 3rdQuarter 5579, ending June 19, 1819; copy of offerings of 4thQuarter 5579, ending September 18, 1819 (separated from Box 2, Item #160) (Box 13(OS6), Folder 5)
  - List of offerings for 4thQuarter 5577-1817 (separated from Box 4, Item #267) (Box 13(OS6), Folder 6)
  - Exterior Beth Elohim (separated from Box 8, J.J. Lyons Scrapbook) (Box 13(OS6), Folder 7)
  - Recommendation letter for Rev. J.J. Lyons, written by members of K.K. Beth Shalom (separated from Box 1, Item #7), 1839 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 8)
  - Account of Isaac K. Abraham De Peyster to Estate of Miguel Pacheco DaSilva (separated from Box 1, Item #14), 1738-1745 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 9)
  - Statement of the funds of K.K.S.I.(separated from Box 1, Item #47), 1803 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 10)
  - Ground Plan-Mill Street Synagogue (separated from Box 1, Item #60), 1829, June 13, 1871 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 11)
  - Receipt of Jacob Franks for silver from Curaçao towards building synagogue in New York (separated from Box 1, Item #63), 1730 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 12)
  - Petition of Aaron Salom of Jamaica to be hazan (separated from Box 2, Item #83), February 11, 1760 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 13)
  - Citizenship certificate of Isaac Hayman (separated from Box 2, Item #90), March 21, 1797 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 14)
  - List of debts to K.K.S.I.(separated from Box 2, Item #91), 5547 (1787) (Box 14(OS1), Folder 15)
  - Letter to Abraham Pinto regarding insult to Parnas (separated from Box 2, Item #108), 1796 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 16)
  - Bills received and collected of Mr. Lazarus (separated from Box 2, Item #112), 1795 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 17)
  - Treasurer's reports of Hayman Levy (separated from Box 2, Item #114), 1787 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 18)
  - Inventory of K.K.S.I. chest, receipted by Alex. Zuntz, with note by Isaac H. Levy (separated from Box 2, Item #116), July 25, 1784 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 19)
  - Synagogue account with Manuel Myers (separated from Box 2, Item #127), 1793-1795 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 20)
  - Contract between K.K.S.I and Gershom Seixas regarding school (separated from Box 2, Item #147), July 1793 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 21)
  - Copy of letter of K.K.S.I. to London regarding selection of a hazan (separated from Box 3, Item #172), March 13, 1758 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 22)
  - Letter of trustees of K.K.S.I. to Newport congregation regarding joint letter to Pres. Washington (separated from Box 3, Item #175), June 20, 1790 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 23)
  - Letter from congregation in Newport asking K.K.S.I. for help in building a synagogue (separated from Box 3, Item #180), March 21, 1759 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 24)
  - Moses Seixas' accounts for Newport Congregation (separated from Box 3, Item #185), 1784-1790 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 25)
  - Report of committee of K.K.S.I. on several matters (separated from Box 3, Item #187), July 24, 1791 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 26)
  - Address to K.K.S.I. regarding Polonies Talmud Torah (separated from Box 3, Item #194), 1804 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 27)
  - Women in the congregation in the days of Hazan I.B. Seixas (separated from Box 3, Item #197), undated (Box 14(OS1), Folder 28)
  - Letter to K.K.S.I. from K.K. B'nai Jeshurun, asking to borrow seforim and ornaments for the consecration of the synagogue (separated from Box 3, Item #198), June 27, 1827 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 29)
  - Letter of Rev. Joseph J. Pinto to K.K.S.I. announcing his intention to return to Europe (separated from Box 3, Item #200), December 22, 1765 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 30)
  - Letter of Joseph J. Pinto (separated from Box 3, Item #201), July 11, 1759 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 31)
  - Lists of Notes remaining unpaid, Shearith Israel, no. 11; Treasurer, July Balance dues by the Congregation; Sundry account of the Congregation of K.K., August 11, 1795; Account, 1815, 1819 (separated from Box 3, Item #218a) (Box 14(OS1), Folder 32)
  - List of debts due the Congregation Shearith Israel as per Ledger C, 2 mylar sleeves (separated from Box 3, Item #218b), undated (Box 14(OS1), Folder 33)
  - Five receipts (separated from Box 3, Item #218d), November-December 1806 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 34a)
  - Pension (separated from Box 3, Item #218d), 1815 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 34b)
  - Oath of allegiance to George II by Jews in American colonies (separated from Box 3, Item #224), 1741 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 35)
  - Letter of Jews of Amsterdam to Jews of Baltimore, regarding Jews of the Holy Land (separated from Box 3, Item #225), 1823 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 36)
  - Petition to legislature regarding religion in free schools (separated from Box 3, Item #226), January 7, 1813 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 37)
  - Resolution of Trustees, K.K.S.I. to buy ground in Beaver Street, in rear of Mill Street synagogue (separated from Box 4, Item #242), March 21, 1797 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 38)
  - Clerk's list of offerings, 4thquarter (separated from Box 4, Item #245), 1804 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 39)
  - Report of committee to make arrangements for matzah baking (separated from Box 4, Item #246), 1819 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 40)
  - Congregational account (separated from Box 4, Item #250), October 24, 1809 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 41)
  - Letter from Thomas Hope, architect, regarding drawings for ark of new synagogue. Also includes wash drawing of canopy for ark (separated from Box 4, Item #257), January 10, 1818 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 42)
  - Sale of ship "Farmer" to Isaac M. Gomez by Joao Jose Da Silva (separated from Box 4, Item #264), October 21, 1794 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 43)
  - Supposed balance of the year 5555 (separated from Box 4, Item #267) (Box 14(OS1), Folder 44a)
  - List for 4thQuarter 5564 (separated from Box 4, Item #267) (Box 14(OS1), Folder 44b)
  - 2ndQuarter 5565 (separated from Box 4, Item #267) (Box 14(OS1), Folder 44c)
  - Return of offerings to the Sedaka and Poor Fund for the First Quarter 5576 (separated from Box 4, Item #267) (Box 14(OS1), Folder 44d)
  - J.H. Levy's List of offerings for 4thQuarter 5577-1817 (separated from Box 4, Item #267) (Box 14(OS1), Folder 44e)
  - Offerings 2ndQuarter 5579 (separated from Box 4, Item #267) (Box 14(OS1), Folder 44f)
  - Offerings 1stQuarter 5580 Commenced 20 September 1819 (separated from Box 4, Item #267), September 20, 1819 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 44g)
  - Return offerings 2ndQuarter Ending 11 March 1820 (separated from Box 4, Item #267), March 11, 1820 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 44h)
  - 3rdQuarter 5580 (separated from Box 4, Item #267), 5580 (1820) (Box 14(OS1), Folder 44i)
  - Evening Service Anniversary Consecration (separated from Box 4, Item #267), undated (Box 14(OS1), Folder 44j)
  - Financial statement for K.K.S.I.(separated from Box 4, Item #272), 1803 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 45)
  - Ketubah of Hayman Levy and Sloe Myers [Copy of](separated from Box 5, Item #296), May 15, 1751 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 46)
  - Letter (Ladino/Spanish)(separated from Box 5, Item #300.1), 1763 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 47)
  - [#5]: Daniel Gomez and Barbados account with Isaac and Benjamin Gomez (separated from Box 6, Fragments of the Daniel Gomez ledger books), 1747-1749 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 48a)
  - [#9]: Mr. Daniel Gomez…Account current with Gonsales and Mendes DaCosta…February 1754 (separated from Box 6, Fragments of the Daniel Gomez ledger books), 1753-1754 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 48b)
  - [#10]: (Mr.?) Lyon Lepmon to Dan? Gomez (separated from Box 6, Fragments of the Daniel Gomez ledger books), 1739-1742 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 48c)
  - [#11]: Mr. Levy Samuel to Daniel Gomez (separated from Box 6, Fragments of the Daniel Gomez ledger books), 1741-1742 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 48d)
  - [#16]: Account with John Morrey (separated from Box 6, Fragments of the Daniel Gomez ledger books), 1744-1746 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 48e)
  - [#21]: Misters Daniel and Moses Gomez…August 1749 (separated from Box 6, Fragments of the Daniel Gomez ledger books), 1748-1749 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 48f)
  - [#37]: notes of sale of pork in Jamaica and other misc.(separated from Box 6, Fragments of the Daniel Gomez ledger books), undated (Box 14(OS1), Folder 48g)
  - Watercolor of first Bnai Jeshrun, Watercolor of Grand Island, Interior Beth Elohim, Charleston (separated from Box 8, J.J. Lyons Scrapbook) (Box 14(OS1), Folder 49a)
  - Newspaper clippings, notices (separated from Box 8, J.J. Lyons Scrapbook), July 23, 1853 (Box 14(OS1), Folder 49b)
  - Passover Groceries at D. Behrman's 72 Bowery, 1848; Attached to the item is "The Gates of Prayer, Trustee-Room, November 7, 5608"-Conditions for obtaining seats in the new Synagogue in Wooster Street (separated from Box 8, J.J. Lyons Scrapbook) (Box 14(OS1), Folder 50)